Guide to the Lienhard Bergel Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Lienhard Bergel Papers,
1928-1995
Bergel, Lienhard, 1905-1987.
3.5 linear ft (ca. 1,485 items in 7 boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027
4078535
Biographical Note
Lienhard Bergel (1905-1987) was born in Silesia, Germany, and emmigrated to the United States in 1931, where he obtained a position as Instructor in the German Department of the New Jersy College for Women. In 1935 he was refused reappointment because, he claimed, his anti-Nazi views conflicted with those of the Department Head, Johannes Friedrich Hauptmann. The matter was investigated by a special committee of Rutger's University in 1935 and again in 1986. Both panels found the discharge of Bergel justified. Bergel later went on to teach at Queens College and the Graduate Center of the City University of New York (1938-1974). His writings include Cervantes in Germany; Croce, Blake, Goethe; and The Esthetics of Nihilism.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, photographs, printed material, and memorabilia. The cataloged correspondence is with Jacques Barzun, Benedetto Croce, Elena Croce, Wallace Fowlie, Thomas Mann, Salvatore Quasimodo, Arthur Schlesinger Jr., and René Wellek. There is manuscript material relating to the Bergel-Hauptman case and a number of Bergel's own essays and reviews. A copy of Bergel's German passport is included, as well as numerous family photographs and miscellaneous printed material. There is a cataloged photograph of Hugo von Hofmannsthal; and a gold Benedetto Croce centennial medal.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
Series III: Cataloged Photographs
Series IV: Arranged Correspondence
Series V: Arranged Manuscripts
Series VI: Memorabilia
Series VII: Sylvia Bergel Papers
Subjects
Barzun, Jacques, 1907-; Croce, Benedetto, 1866-1952.; Croce, Elena, 1915-; Fowlie, Wallace, 1908-1998.; Hofmannsthal, Hugo von, 1874-1929.; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955.; Quasimodo, Salvatore, 1901-1968.; Schlesinger, Arthur M. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007.; Wellek, René.; Hauptmann, Johannes Friedrich.; Correspondence; Memorabilia; Photoprints; College teachers
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
02/29/88 M-88-02-19 Bergel, Mrs. Lienhard Gift.
2000 Bergel, Mrs. Lienhard Gift.
Gift of Sylvia Bergel, 1988 and Thomas Bergel for the Estate of Sylvia Bergel, 2000
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Barzun, Jacques (Box 1)
  - Croce, Benedetto To Lienhard Bergel, 1866-1952 (Box 1)
  - Croce, Elena To Lienhard Bergel, 1915- (Box 1)
  - Fowlie, Wallace To Lienhard Bergel (Box 1)
  - Mann, Thomas To Lienhard Bergel, 1875-1955 (Box 1)
  - Quasimodo, Salvatore To Lienhard Bergel, 1901-1968 (Box 1)
  - Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr. To Lienhard Bergel (Box 1)
  - Wellek, Rene, To Lienhard Bergel (Box 1)
- II. Cataloged Manuscripts
  - Bergel, Lienhard, 1905-1987 (Box 1)
- III. Cataloged Photographs
  - Bergel, Lienhard (Box 1)
  - Croce, Benedetto (Box 1)
  - Hofmannsthal, Hugo von (Box 1)
- IV. Arranged Correspondence
  - Bergel, Lienhard To Croce, ((photocopies)) (Box 1)
  - Bergel, Lienhard To Quasimodo (Box 1)
  - Bergel, Lienhard To various correspondents (Box 1)
  - Letters to Bergel, 1931-1985 (Box 1)
  - Postcards to Bergel (Box 1)
- V. Arranged Manuscripts
  - Bergel-Hauptmann case (Box 1)
  - Course material (Box 1)
  - Testimonial (Box 1)
  - Bergel manuscripts (Box 2)
  - Bergel manuscripts, and 3 manuscripts, in German, by others (Box 3)
  - Bergel's passport (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous printed material and a copy of W.H. Auden's The Enchaged Flood (Box 3)
- VI. Memorabilia
  In the Vault
  - 1. Gold Benedetto Croce centennial medal in presentation case (Box 4)
  - 2. Mother-of-pearl barrel-shaped case with hinged top and bottom. 2.5 inches. (Box 4)
  - 3. Rectangular bowl with stem and base, leaf pattern on lip. 2 ¼ x 2 x 2 ¼ inches. (Box 4)
  - 4 Small base metal bucket, with handle and chain. 4 inches high. (Box 4)
  - 5 Small base metal bowl on three legs. 2 inches diameter. (Box 4)
  - 6. Clay figure of a goat at rest. (Box 4)
- VII. Sylvia Bergel Papers
  The correspondence in this series was originally in chronological order but has been arranged by correspondent. Duplicates of correspondence and newspaper clippings were removed.
  - 7.1 Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1905-1987 (Box 5)
    - Bergel, Lienhard Letters to the Editor, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Bloustein, Edward, 1925-1989 and Rutgers University, 1985-1989 (Box 5)
    - Greenberg, Michael, 1987-1992 (Box 5)
    - Horn, Daniel, 1985 (Box 5)
    - McCormick, Richard, 1916-, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    - Oshinsky, David, 1944-, 1985-1993 (Box 5)
    - Parisi, Peter, 1941-, 1985-1989 (Box 5)
    - Silver, Alan, 1914-1988, 1985-1989 (Box 5)
    - Simon Wiesenthal Center, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Zenchelsky, Seymour, 1987-1995 (Box 6)
    - Letters to the Editor, 1985-1995 (Box 6)
    - Various correspondence A-B (Box 6)
    - Various correspondence C (Box 6)
    - Various correspondence D-M (Box 6)
    - Various correspondence N-Z (Box 6)
    - Index to correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 6)
  - 7.2 Writings by Others
    - Greenberg, Michael and Zenchelsky, Seymour "Anti-Semitism at Rutgers: the 1920s and 30s", 1993 (Box 6)
    - Greenberg, Michael and Zenchelsky, Seymour "The Confrontation with Nazism at Rutgers: Academic Bureaucracy and Moral Failure", 1990 (Box 6)
    - Oshinsky, David "Report on the Bergel-Hauptmann Case", 1986 (Box 6)
    - American Civil Liberties Union "Reports of Investigators…on Trustees' Investigation into Dismissal of Lienhard Bergel from the German Department at the New Jersey College for Women", August 1935 (Box 6)
    - Amercian Association of University Professors "Report on the Bergel Matter", February 1987 (Box 6)
    - Special Trustees' Committee Report. "In the Matter of the Investigation of the Charges of Lienhard Bergel", August 1935 (Box 7)
      [Copied 1985]
    - Bergel, Sylvia Research notes, Compiled 1985 (Box 7)
    - Bergel, Syvlia Notes and drafts of correspondence, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Bergel, Sylvia Bibliography of Lienhard Bergel's publications, 1989 (Box 7)
  - 7.3 Subject/Topical Files
    - 7.3.1 Bergel-Hauptmann case
      - Letters of Hauptmann, Clothier and Corwin 1940-1941, Photocopied 1985 (Box 7)
    - 7.3.2. German Academy
      - Translation by Sylvia Bergel, 1985 (Box 7)
    - 7.3.3. FBI
      - FBI file on Johannes Hauptmann, Photocopied 1986 (Box 7)
  - 7.4 Documents
    - Faculty Questionnaire filled in by Lienhard Bergel, 1967, (Photocopy, ) (Box 7)
    - Lienhard Bergel's teaching certificates, 1930 (Box 7)
  - 7.5 Photographs
    - Alan Silver Alan Silver's dog, 1989 (Box 7)
  - 7.6 Printed Material
    - Biographies photocopied from various sources (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1933-1992 (Box 7)